<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Turkes secretorie conteining his sundrie letters sent to diuers emperours, kings, princes and states, full of proud bragges, and bloody threatnings: with seuerall answers to the same, both pithie and peremptorie. Translated truly out of the Latine copie.</title>
            <title>Epistolae magni Turci. English</title>
            <author>Mehmed II, Sultan of the Turks, 1432-1481.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07604</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112757</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848002</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848002</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13074</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07604)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13074)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 722:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Turkes secretorie conteining his sundrie letters sent to diuers emperours, kings, princes and states, full of proud bragges, and bloody threatnings: with seuerall answers to the same, both pithie and peremptorie. Translated truly out of the Latine copie.</title>
                  <title>Epistolae magni Turci. English</title>
                  <author>Mehmed II, Sultan of the Turks, 1432-1481.</author>
                  <author>Laudivio, de Vezzano.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M[elchisedec] B[radwood] and are to be solde at the Swan in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ostensibly by Mehmet II.</note>
                  <note>A translation of "Epistolae magni Turci", compiled by Laudivio de Vezzano and sometimes attributed to him.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The Turkes secretorie. 1607.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turkey --  History --  Mehmet II, 1452-1481 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13074:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13074:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TVRKES SECRETORIE, Conteining HIS SVNDRIE LETTERS Sent to diuers Emperours, Kings, Princes and States, full of proud bragges, and bloody threatnings:</p>
            <p>With ſeuerall Anſwers to the ſame, both pithie and peremptorie.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated truly out of the Latine Copie.</p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by M. B. and are to be ſolde at the Swan in Pauls Church-yard. 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13074:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13074:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST Woorthie, <hi>Liborius, Theodore, Adolph, Lodowick,</hi> and <hi>George,</hi> ſonnes to the moſt noble <hi>Nicolas</hi> of MVNI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHAVSEN, fauourers of all good learning, health.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>OST noble and woorthie Gentlemen,</hi> the birth and growth of <hi>Mahomets</hi> tyranny, which, like the inundation of ſome great and mightie riuer, hath ouerflowen the greatest part of the world, is very me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morable. For that <hi>Arabian</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor and falſe Prophet, being deſcended of meane parentage, vnder colour of a certaine new and plauſible Religion, made his way to the Empire; and hauing therewith good ſucceſſe and fortune of warre, was the first that gaue name to that ſuperſtitious ſect, and moſt prodigious king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And indeed this enterpriſe was more eaſily atchieued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, in all counſels and contractations he had an excellent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, and affected alwayes in his deſignments and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be popular. For being by nature compoſed all of Subtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Flatterie, he became by meanes thereof ſo powerfull and mightie in his perſuaſions, that in ſhort time he drew all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to his partie, and purchaſte himſelfe a great name and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation amongst them.</p>
            <p>The lawes and inſtitutions which he publiſhed, were imbraced of his countrey-men with woonderfull applauſe and liking, partly, for that he pretended to haue receiued them by Diuine inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and partly, becauſe they held good correſpondence and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with their owne wicked inclination, and diſſolute courſe of
<pb facs="tcp:13074:3"/>
life. And this courſe ſeemed vnto him to be the ſhorteſt and moſt compendious way to attaine and eſtabliſh his greatneſſe, being perſwaded that where he could not obtaine in a Lions skin, there doubtleſſe he ſhould preuaile in a Foxes caſe. For he called to minde, how <hi>Lyſander</hi> had once aduiſed to that purpoſe, deriding the follie of thoſe men, who (as if they were borne of <hi>Hercules</hi>) ſeeke to accompliſh their deſignments rather with force than with policie.</p>
            <p>But of the maner of gouernment among the <hi>Lacedaemonians,</hi> being very like to this, and of that wicked <hi>Alcoran</hi> which was patched together by the labour and trauell of thoſe leud confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Antioch, Sergius</hi> the <hi>Arrian,</hi> and a certaine Iew that was an <hi>Aſtronomer,</hi> in the yeere of our Sauiour Christ, <hi>624.</hi> and in the time of Heraclius the Emperour, and of <hi>Pope Honorius</hi> the firſt; though a great field is heere opened vnto me to diſcourſe, yet at this time, and at this place I hold it needleſſe and impertinent. To returne therefore to our former matter.</p>
            <p>When he had ordered his affaires after this maner, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the people, that were madde with deſire of libertie, to take armes; wherewith he enlarged the narrow confines of his <hi>new Monarchie,</hi> and in ſhort time brought great and mightie Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces to be ſubiect to his tyrannie. The people were encouraged heerein the rather, through a vaine hope, wherewith this falſe <hi>Arabian</hi> prophet did abuſe them, making them beleeue, that they ſhould be <hi>Maiſters</hi> of the whole world: which (as he ſaide) both by Diuine Prouidence, and right of inheritance did apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine vnto <hi>Abrahams</hi> poſteritie, and conſequently vnto them, who deriued their petigree lineally from <hi>Sara</hi> their mother. This vaine conceit was a ſtrong goade to pricke them forwards to make ſharpe and cruell warres againſt all nations. And to this day, the <hi>Turkes</hi> made proud with this fancie onely, haue with their armes inuaded diuers Kingdomes and States, and like an heard of hungrie wolues, lying in wait for a flocke of ſheepe, they lie in ambuſh to deſtroie all <hi>Chriſtendome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither was <hi>Mahomet</hi> the ſecond leſſe agreeable in conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons than in Name, to that <hi>Enthuſiaſticall</hi> ſeducer, exerciſing
<pb facs="tcp:13074:3"/>
more tyrannie and crueltie, than all the <hi>Ottamanes</hi> beſides, as if the ſame had beene bequeathed vnto him by the last Will and Testament of his predeceſſour. For his father <hi>Amurathes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe of all that euer liued, the moſt barbarous and cruell, declared him to be the heire apparant of all his kingdomes and ſeignories, vpon condition, that he would be an euerlaſting ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the name of Chriſt, and would bend all his ſtudies, and thoughts, to be tyrannous, cruell, and vnmercifull. But ſo ſtraight a band and caution needed not, ſeeing the exceeding paleneſſe of his countenance, hauing ſwolne cheekes, and a crooked noſe which touched almoſt his lippes, together with manie other ſignes and tokens of a monstrous nature, ſhewed euidently in his childhood, what kinde of man he was like to prooue in his riper yeeres. For he that readeth the Hiſtories of former times, ſhall finde many examples of ſuch miſ-ſhapen and deformed <hi>Therſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> the monſters and wonders of Man-kind, which haue beene in their time, the ruine and confuſion of Kingdomes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weales.</p>
            <p>His Mother, being the daughter of the <hi>Deſpote</hi> of <hi>Seruia,</hi> and <hi>Duke</hi> of Myſia, was carefull to inſtruct him in the rules of Pietie and Chriſtian Religion. For holding in deepe detestation the wicked hereſies of the Saracens, and the ſauage crueltie of the Barbarous Turkes, ſhe deſired earneſtly to haue him conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to the obedience of Chriſt, and ſeruice of the Common-wealth: which, being herſelfe a wiſe and religious woman, ſhe preferred as a heauenly treaſure before all the wealth and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of tho world. But,
<q>Naturam expellas furca, &amp;c.</q>
Nature will not be bridled, and what is bred in the bone will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer out of the fleſh. For <hi>Mahomet</hi> no ſooner came to mans eſtate, but he caſt all into the winde, and tooke no care of any reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. In priuate he was an abſolute <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> repoſing all his hopes in a good <hi>Fortune,</hi> making no account of the Diuine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, and with many ſcoffes and ſcornes teſting at thoſe which affirmed that humane affaires are diſpoſed and gouerned by God.</p>
            <p>Wherefore following the example and direction of his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour
<pb facs="tcp:13074:4"/>
and father, his chiefeſt care and ſtudie was to enlarge his dominions, and with the yoke of Mahometane ſlauerie to oppreſſe thoſe kings and people whom he ſubdued. So that in the ſpace of <hi>32.</hi> yeeres, that he raigned, many Kingdomes, Dukedomes, and Cities were conquered, and became ſubiect to his tyrannie. For which cauſe he was compared to Alexander the Great, and for his noble and great exploits, ſurnamed the <hi>Great</hi> amongſt his people.</p>
            <p>The firſt and fearefulleſt feate of warre which he did, was the winning of <hi>Bizantium</hi> the moſt renowned and Famous Citie of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, which is acknowledged of all, to haue beene the glory aad beauty of all Chriſtendome. There is no man liuing (as I thinke) that is able with fit words, and due compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to expreſſe ſo greeuous and ſo great calamities. For then the great and mighty Empire of Greece that was wont to be the wall and bulwarke of the <hi>Romane Empire,</hi> in leſſe than two moneths ſiege was diſſolued, and vtterly ſubuerted. The Emperour <hi>Conſtantinus Paleologus,</hi> a Prince endued with all commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable parts of piety, and vertue, ſeeing his eſtate was deſperat, and thinking to eſcape with his people at a backe gate, was miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſmothered and killed in the throng: at what time, the bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and cruell tyrant cauſed Proclamation to be made, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of what age, ſex, or condition ſoeuer ſhould be ſaued or pitied in that common maſſacre. This lamentable tragedy was acted in the <hi>1453.</hi> yeere after the recouery of our ſaluation by the <hi>Sonne of God,</hi> when <hi>Fredericke</hi> the third ſwaied the Empire of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth gouerned the Papacy.</p>
            <p>Now God of his infinite goodneſſe and mercy breake the rod and power of the Turkes, and ſtop their rage and fury, that in theſe latter daies which are yet remaining vnto the day of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Church may enioy peace and ſafety. For we are come now vnto that time, wherein many graue, wiſe, and learned perſons, among whom <hi>Luther</hi> was not the meaneſt, foretold that the Turke ſhould raigne in <hi>Germany.</hi> And truely ſo it appeareth. For all their ſtudies and forces are bent only, that by a ſhort cut they may inuade our borders. And if we marke with
<pb facs="tcp:13074:4"/>
what ciuill diſſentions, and inteſtine broiles the whole country of Germany is ſet on fire, we cannot but confeſſe that it will be an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie enterpriſe for them to ſubdue it; except our moſt gratious and mercifull God being pacified with our humble deuotions, will with his inuincible arme defend vs and avert theſe dangers.</p>
            <p>The Turkes (we ſee) with all diligence and watchfulneſſe, doe obſerue ſuch aduantages, and ſeldome or neuer doe they ſlip theſe occaſions, but with great ioy embrace them, as the only ſignes and abodements of their good fortune: whereas we are poſſeſſed with ſuch dulneſſe and ſtupidity, (what ſhall I call it elſe? more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly I can call it nothing) that, beſides it depriueth vs of all ſenſe of our owne miſeries, it cauſeth alſo in our enemies themſelues ſo great an admiration and wonderment, that they ieſt at vs for it with extreame laughter and deriſion.</p>
            <p>How happy were it for vs, if the great wealth whereof the Exchequer, and common Treaſury is daily emptied, were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploied on this ſeruice, and the ſubiects were not ſuffered to be ſo much impoueriſhed as they are? For ſo long as they are rich, and able to contribute to their Soueraignes wants, it will be an eaſie matter to raiſe an Army and to make warre vpon any occaſion: But if once they be exhauſted and drawne drie with vnneceſſary exactions and impoſitions, our armies will ſoone be diſſolued, and our warres will prooue ridiculous and infortunate, for want of meanes to proſecute and maintaine them. And if then neceſſity compell vs to ſeeke for peace, and Chriſtian amity with our foes, is it not ſtrange that in time of proſperity the very name of peace is ſo odious and hatefull? eſpecially conſidering it happeneth many times, that whileſt two are ſtriuing and contending together, they are made (like the frog and the mouſe in the fable) a pray and booty to a third enemy, whoſe malice neuer ceaſeth till he hath deſtroied them both, and ſent their ſoules (that I may vſe the Poets words) to fery ouer the <hi>Stygian</hi> lake, which is the blacke pit of hell.</p>
            <p>Why then are we afraid of any forrain Turks? Seeing we, euen we, are Turkes vnto our ſelues: yea farre more cruell and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious than any Turke, or (as the name importeth) any deſtroier
<pb facs="tcp:13074:5"/>
in the world. For the Turks, being at peace within themſelues, doe beare one common hatred againſt all Chriſtians, that they may ſubdue them, and deſtroy their name and memory from the earth: But on the other ſide, we make peace with Turks, and turne our ſwords againſt our owne ſides, hauing our pleaſure only, with ciuill warres and domeſticke broiles, to deſtroy one another, as if we had conſpired with the common enemy, to make ourſelues an eaſie conqueſt vnto his tyranny. And if this be not madneſſe and fury, I know not what is madneſſe. But let vs returne to <hi>Mahomet:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who, although he was of ſuch a tyrannous nature, as I haue declared, yet contrary to al other Barbarians, hath this praiſe and commendation giuen him by all Hiſtoriographers, namely that he burned alwaies with an incredible deſire to vnderſtand all good Arts and Hiſtories. For he cauſed the Hiſtories of all Nations, hauing to his infinite charge gathered them together out of all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to be tranſlated into the Turkiſh tongue, that they might ſerue him as a well-furniſhed ſtore-houſe of graue examples, fit for imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and practiſe, in the vſe of warre, and military diſcipline: What kind of ſtratagems and war-like policies he hath gathered out of them, his owne manner of Gouernment, and the Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries of <hi>Vicentinus,</hi> his freed-bondman, and of many others that haue written thereof, doe declare at large. Among the reſt, theſe Epiſtles, being ſo wittily, and grauely written, deſerue not the leaſt nor the laſt commendation. For they were written by himſelfe, either as he marched and ſet foorth againſt his enemies, or elſe when he encamped: againſt whoſe teſtimonie, being moſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy to his owne reſolutions and warre-like affaires, there is no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception can be taken. And where he vſeth in them a certaine kind of <hi>Laconicall</hi> breuity, it is not for want of time to write more largely, but becauſe his deſire was alwaies to expreſſe his minde in a full and plaine kind of ſpeech, without vaine and needleſſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. For they that are wiſe indeed, are euer accuſtomed to deliuer much matter in few words: which praiſe <hi>Homer</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnto <hi>Menelaus</hi> the Spartan, and many other great perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages are commended by others, for the ſame quality and vertue.
<pb facs="tcp:13074:5"/>
Yet I deny not, but this witty and conciſe kind of ſpeech which <hi>Mahomet</hi> vſeth, doth ſauour very much of tyranny: becauſe it is common with Tyrants to deliuer their minds in few termes, and thoſe alſo very imperious and menacing, as their owne verſe declareth;
<q>Sic volo, ſic iubeo, ſtat pro ratione voluntas.</q>
               <q>
                  <l>So doe I will, So I command,</l>
                  <l>And let my will for reaſon ſtand.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>As for the reſponſory letters, which are wouen in the ſame loome, I haue no more to ſay, but that they ſhew a manifeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Tyrant and his threatnings, holding it farre better to hazard the worſt of Fortune, then to yeeld their nekes to the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell yoake of his intolerable ſlauery. But to let paſſe all Hiſtories, is it not a lamentable thing to conſider, how he hath ſubdued and conquered all places that he came vnto? ſo that he may truely ſay of himſelfe, as once ſaid <hi>Iulius Caeſar:</hi>
               <q>Veni, Vidi, Vici.</q>
               <q>I came, I ſaw, I ouercame.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much ſhall ſuffice of him. Now concerning the Tranſlatour of theſe Epiſtles, (one <hi>Laudinius</hi> a man famous and well knowen to the world, as well for his learning, as for the honour and place which hee had amongst the Knights of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi>) he deſerueth no leſſe praiſe for tranſlating, then the Authour himſelfe for compoſing them. For he hath ſo liuely and ſignificantly expreſſed the conceit and meaning of a ſtrange tongue, that he ſeemeth altogether to reliſh of <hi>Tullie</hi> his ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy and ſweetneſſe. Therefore my hope is, that good men will not diſlike my trauels in publiſhing the ſame; which hauing fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, I thought good to dedicate the ſame to you, <hi>moſt noble and worthy Gentlemen.</hi> For I vnderſtand by good and credible re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that you doe apply your whole ſtudy vnto learning and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb facs="tcp:13074:6"/>
and that no day paſſeth you without ſome time drawen to that purpoſe. Aſſuredly, though you are diſcended of many moſt ancient and noble Gentlemen, and may iuſtly boaſt the honorable badges and armes of your Anceſtours; yet the beſt and readieſt way to raiſe your titles, and to make you more honorable, is to be learned. Which way if you will purſue with your accuſtomed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, you ſhall ſhortly reape the happy fruits of your long ſtudies, namely, variety of all perfect and true knowledge, and a noble reputation graced with the beſt preferments both with Prince and people: The one being enabled through your graue and learned counſels, will gouern his eſtate vertuouſly, and the other hauing confidence in your vertue, will feare no dangers. O happy, and thriſe happy are they, to whom ſuch bleſſings are giuen of God. Indeed the common ſort of Gentlemen, of whom <hi>Carneades</hi> ſometimes ſpake, becauſe they learne nothing but to ride horſes are in no eſtimation, no not with the meaneſt of the multitude. For is there any thing in them, that appeareth worthy or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable? Cannot euery vulgar and baſe fellow learne to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage a horſe aſwell as they? Which I ſpeake not to diſgrace ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and horſmanſhip: but wiſh rather it may haue it's due ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reſpect: only I would not haue you to be of their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber who giuing themſelues wholy to this quality make ſlow procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings or none at all in the way of learning; wherein I doubt not, but your fathers iudgment doth concurre with mine, as I might well perceiue at my firſt acquaintance with him, when in the Caſtle of <hi>Stradthag</hi> I taught that worthy and noble Gentleman, <hi>Count Erneſtus,</hi> the true and ſole heire of the Countie of <hi>Schoum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi> For conſidering with himſelfe, what great commodities learning bringeth with it to all ſorts of perſons, his principall care and ſtudy was to commit you to the hands of graue and learned teachers, to be inſtructed, and to prouide for you according to your eſtates, competent and neceſſarie exhibition. For all which his fatherly care and bounty, he requireth no more of you but to be diligent to furniſh your ſelues with all good learning and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Which if you will doe, you will reioice the harts not only of
<pb facs="tcp:13074:6"/>
your parents, but alſo of all thoſe that loue you, and you ſhall be highly esteemed amongst the chiefeſt Nobilitie. But it is needleſſe to ſpurre a free horſe, or to exhort you that are alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die prepared and addreſſed to this vertuous courſe. Therefore I will ſtay my ſelfe heere, humblie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching you to take in good part this ſlender ſignification of my dutious affection towards you and your ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. Fare you well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Hon: moſt deuoted M. HERMANN. VASTELLAB.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:13074:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE OF LAVDINIVS <hi>Knight of Hieruſalem,</hi> written to <hi>Francinus Beltrardus concerning the</hi> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Great <hi>Turke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O whom rather (my deare <hi>Francinus</hi>) ſhould I ſend the letters which I haue late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſhed, then vnto you? wherein I haue ſought more to pleaſe my ſelfe, then to be praiſed of others: for hauing retired my ſelfe for my recreation to <hi>Cicianum,</hi> a towne in Campania, I thought good to preſent theſe vnto you, that thereby I might tender you an account both of my diligence and ſtudies. The Commentaries which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to write to the Pope, the greatneſſe of the worke com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled me to giue ouer vntill an other time. I know that heerein I doe expoſe my ſelfe to the detraction of many; conſidering how moſt men are ſo froward and peeuiſh in their opinions, that they will iudge nothing according to right, but will meaſure all things by their owne reaſon. And ſo ſeeing we haue loſt the truth long ſithence, I am contented to leaue this cenſure of me to the poſteritie. <hi>Nunc pueri naſum Rhinocero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis habent.</hi> 
               <g ref="char:dtristar">*⁎*</g>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13074:7"/>
            <argument>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE ARGVMENT</hi> of theſe Letters.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAhomet</hi> Emperour of the Turkes, ſur-named for the woorthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his exploits, the <hi>Great Turke,</hi> when (hauing increaſed the forces which his father left him) he had conquered <hi>Aſia,</hi> he tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported ouer <hi>Helleſponte</hi> an infinite armie into Europe, and with the ſame wonne <hi>BiZantium</hi> the famous and noble citie of Conſtantine. He brought alſo to his ſubiection <hi>Myſia, Galatia, Thracia, Achaia, Pelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponneſus, Acarnania, Aetolia, Ambrachia, Epirus,</hi> and all that coaſt of <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyria,</hi> beſides twelue kingdomes in the leſſer <hi>Aſia:</hi> namely, <hi>Pontus, Bithynia, Cappadocia, Paph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>agonia, Cilicia, Pamphilia, Lycia, Caria, Lydia, Phrygia,</hi> and <hi>Helleſpont.</hi> All which are at this day vnder the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Turke: who, (as occaſions preſented themſelues vnto him) directed of late his letters vnto diuers perſons and people of the world; partly in the <hi>Syrian</hi> and <hi>Greeke</hi> tongue, and partly in the Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian or Slauonian. Theſe comming into the handes of <hi>Laudinius</hi> Knight of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> who vnderſtandeth theſe languages perfectlie, were tranſlated by him into the Latin, and are now publiſhed in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh for the good of thoſe that deſire to know the affaires and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Turke.</p>
            </argument>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to <hi>Sancaſſan</hi> king of Perſia.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                  </hi> Doe heare, that thou haſt paſſed <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates,</hi> and haſt brought a great power vnto <hi>Lepta,</hi> that thou art entred with the ſame into the confines of <hi>Parthia,</hi> and there putteſt all to the fire &amp; ſword; that with thy forces thou haſt inuaded <hi>Armenia,</hi> and conueied thine armie thither; and that, hauing ſpoiled the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, thou haſt diuided the townes, villages, and fieldes as a pray to thy ſouldiers. Surely I wonder much that thou beareſt the mind not of a conquerour, but of a robber. Therefore hauing muſtered our people out of all Greece, we make ready to fight with thee, that thou maieſt war with thine enemy with equall forces. For it is baſe and diſhonorable for great and mightie kings, to make warre like theeues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:13074:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Sancaſſan</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>HAuing encamped at the foote of the mountaine <hi>Taurus,</hi> I went preſently in all haſte with the armie to lay ſiege to <hi>Theſiphon:</hi> and hauing waſted all the borders of <hi>Armenia,</hi> I forced all the countrey for feare of my power to obey me. Which maketh me the rather to woonder, that thou doeſt call my deedes in queſtion, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering that as they are many and famous, ſo they haue bene all atchieued after the due courſe of warre and law of Armes. Know therefore, that of our enemies we ſeeke not praiſe, but victorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to <hi>Sancaſſan.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Came with my armie to the ſtraights of Cilicia, where with a memorable ouerthrow <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great ouercame <hi>Darius.</hi> Neither doe we promiſe to our ſelues any other ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of our warres: ſeeing we haue already matched <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in the glorie and fortune of our exploits. For great enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes are not performed by the furie and rage of a rude mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude: but victorie conſiſteth in the proweſſe of a fewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sancaſſan</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVHen I doe conſider my owne power, and the greatneſſe of my noble actes, wherein I haue beene as fortunate as the immortall Gods, I cannot but laugh at thy raſh and fooliſh preparations: eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, hauing alwaies commanded a moſt inuincible army, by whoſe valour I am ſtiled <hi>The most fortunate King.</hi> All the <hi>Bactrians, Perſians, Medes, Armenians, Parthians,</hi> and almoſt the whole Eaſt: I haue ſubdued with my armes: and ſince Alexander the Great, none but I durſt make warres vpon the nations. Ceaſe therefore to boaſt of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13074:8"/>
great fortune of the place at the ſtraights of Cilicia. An In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian Elephant doth not feare a Gnat. There is nothing ſo hard and difficult, but the conſtant reſolution of ſouldiers will ouercome it. And there is no place ſo inacceſſible, but valour will enter it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sexuares</hi> King of Armenia to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVE haue ſent our Ambaſſadours as farre as <hi>Theſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon</hi> vnto <hi>Sancaſſan,</hi> who with incredible prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, hath entered <hi>Meſopotamia,</hi> and march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with a great power to beſiege <hi>Babylon</hi> and <hi>Carras.</hi> Alſo he purpoſeth that <hi>Syria</hi> and all <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhall be a pray vnto him. So numberleſſe an Army and ſo mighty an Hoſt, we remember not to haue euer beene aſſembled in one place: ſo that for his great ſtrength, he ſeemeth to exceed <hi>Xerxes, Darius, Pyrrhus, and Alexander.</hi> Adde hereunto ſix hundred thouſand horſemen, and ſo many footmen. His magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent and ſumptuous prouiſion for the warre, and his tents beſet all about with pearles and pretious ſtones declare eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently that it is a royall preparation. They ſay that he hath in his Tents ſeuen hundred concubines and as many boies. Alſo the Eunuches and Camp-maſters following the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages are reported to be ſix thouſand. Finally, they haue armour and weapons of all ſorts appertaining to the warre: namely, French curans, Spaniſh targets, Romane buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins, Candian arrowes, Parthian bowes, and Aegyptian ſpeares. All which things being carefully diſcouered by our ſpies, we haue ſignified vnto you at large. For who dares attempt any thing raſhly againſt him, that ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be able to contend for ſoueraignty with the Gods themſelues? Or will any man neglect to prouide the beſt he may for his ſafety, when he ſtandeth ſo neere to deſtruction?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:13074:9"/>
               <head>The Turke to <hi>Sexuares.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe things thou haſt ſignified vnto vs by thy Ambaſſadors, touching the prouiſion <hi>Sancaſſanus</hi> makes againſt vs, are ſo farre from amating vs, that they haue animated the mindes of our ſouldiours, and increaſed their wonted courage, for that confidence they haue alwaies had in warre, and hopes, to carrie away the ſpoiles of their enemies, are redoubled by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port: as for concubines, iewels, and other accidentall ornaments of an armie, pertaining to the vnneceſſarie brauerie, and not the true being of a ſouldiour, I eſteeme them to auaile not a ruſh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to victorie: for whiles they are rather a hinderance to the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, they ſeeme to inflame the appetites of our ſouldiours, and whet them vnto the pray: neither yet do we contend about kingly brauerie, delights and dainties, but for victorie, and militarie manhood, whereby kingdomes are purchaſed: as for his num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſſe heapes of men, we ſcorne them; for the baſe vnlette<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red multitude is fitter to flie then fight, readier to take them to their heeles and runne away, then to ſtand for victorie, and win the day.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Soldan</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVHen newes are brought me, how many fields are wonne by thy ſword, and when I heare the great woonders of thy exploits, it will not ſinke into my head, that ſo great things come to paſſe, either by thine owne, or by thy ſouldiours valour; its the hand of Fortune, I rather beleeue, who ouerrules all actions; yet doe I not for all that, enuie any whit thy praiſes: for what generous minde will not commend vertue, euen in an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie? but ſuch verily is the reeling weakeneſſe of humane things, that all things except they be ruled by fatall neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſeeme to be at Ladie Fortunes pleaſure, and after her countenance, rather then to be directed by the wiſedome, and concluded by the hand of man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13074:9"/>
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Soldan.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THou art farre wide, man, and not a little deceiued, to thinke, thoſe men commit all to Fates and Fortune, who worke all by counſell and good aduiſe. Vertue is not ſubiect to be rul'd, nor ouerrul'd by Fortune; but its reaſon, the Lady regent, and mistres of mans houſe, that ouerſwaies in all things, by which we come neerer in nature to the gods, then other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Notwithſtanding, lo thee heere a reaſon of the things haue beene done by vs, ſo many and ſo great. If we want no trustie wakefull centonels to watch; if we haue good ſtore of well diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and old trained ſouldiers; if we haue plentie of freſh water ſouldiours of good hope, pickt out of all degrees; if our armie be puiſſant, accuſtomed well to ouercome, but knowes not how to be ouercom'd; an armie, that can liue long winters a moſt hardie life in tents; exerciſed with great iourneies, expoſed to manie dangers, hardned with manifold labours by ſea and land; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with no occaſion of warre, whoſe forefront neuer yet yeelded one foote of ground, no man daring to turne his backe; an army that hath learned patience to endure both hot and cold, neither caſt downe with aduerſitie, nor lifted vp with proſperitie; that by vertue hath made triumphes of all euils, that by warfare tho farre from home, hath brought vnder their girdle innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nations of the world, and often put to flight incredible troupes of men; for which I my ſelfe ſtand eſtabliſhed Emperour of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the Eaſt. Now, if you call all theſe things Fortune, if you will haue all theſe to be plaid by happe hazard, then I confeſſe all things are turned vp and downe, to riſe or fall, as Fortunes ſmile or frowne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the Pope of Rome.</head>
               <p>VVE haue inuaded Corinthus with armes, the moſt noble citie of Achaia; we haue beſides ſet foote in Aetolia, aduanced our colour in Macedonia, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13074:10"/>
marched the pace of victorie through all Peloponneſus from end to end; the villages, cornefields, and townes, that ſtood in our way we haue ſpoiled farre and neere by fire, and turned them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſmoake, to make way before vs, that without any let, we may make warre vpon Italy, and Rome at last to ſtoupe. All theſe things doe we let thee to vnderſtand to the great terrour, and greater loſſe of all Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Pope of Rome to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVE minde to reuenge, not ſo much thy bloudy cruelty in putting all Greece to fire and ſword, as the ſpoiles and ruines of ſo many famous Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for how may we hope thou ſhouldſt ſo temper victory, that thou wilt ſhew mercy and vſe clemency towards thine enemies, who neuer yet ſparedſt thine owne in cruelty, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and luſt? neither can there be any thing kept right or holy in actions tweene man and man when God is had in contempt, and Gods religion in neglect; we haue not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ſo at thy hands, that thou ſhouldſt bring warre vpon Italy, and beare armes againſt Rome; yet ſhall we be able, to contemne with eaſe the vniuſt armes of wicked men, who haue the armes of God to gard vs, and dwell ſecure vnder the wings of heauens protection.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the Pope of Rome.</head>
               <p>IN vaine, by great God Mahomet I ſweare, doeſt thou reaſon the caſe with vs, who meane not to ſtriue with thee about holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; nor is religion the golden ball we run for; nor yet is Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice the end and aime of our ſwords; but the bent of our deſires is to inlarge the bounds of our Empire; let the better cauſe be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his that hath the field, let him be iuſter in his plea, that ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is in armes: as for cruelty, and luſt, two things thou haſt ſo burdened vs withal, know thou, we therefore practiſe them vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our captiues, becauſe we would not haue our fame to belie vs,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13074:10"/>
but that men may finde me the very ſame indeed, whom fame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports me in words.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Pope of Rome to the Turke.</head>
               <p>ALthough our cauſe which moues vs to warre againſt thee be moſt iuſt, yet haue we taken arms vpon vs not with like wickedneſſe to thee, only in a luſt of Lordly raining, but in a neceſſity of defending our liberty. For who can with patience beare a Tyrant? What man can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure ſo damnable and vnmanly manners? For looke, whats vſuall in others, when feare, hate, or anger mooues them vnto bitterneſſe againſt their vnderlings, thou of thy ſelfe and voluntary motion without any other motiue art more barbarous then they all, who glorieſt more in cruelty then victory it ſelfe, vpbraiding the captiues with their miſery, to make them more miſerable. Expect therefore to pay, what thou oweſt, deſerued puniſhments for thy miſdeeds; for God though he hath leaden heels, yet he hath iron hands, and will recompence the ſlow pace of reuenge, with the greater blow of paiment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Venetians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Came vnto Patra with ſo mighty an Army, that I ouercame with a looke; the firſt ſtep was victory; and at firſt ſight all was mine owne. Theſe are the things we let you to vnderſtand with the no little dammage of your Common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Venetians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>IT was neither by experience of warre, nor valour of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours, thou ouercameſt vs at Patra: fortune muſt haue all the thanks. Who ſeeing ſhe is not in the hands and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of men, well maieſt thou feare one day to prooue, what others now feele; looke thou therefore for a change, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13074:11"/>
an ebtide of that fortune, thou now ſo fondly and lightly boaſteſt in; for peace hath the praiſe of victory, where more is done by the will and pleaſure of Fortune, then is foreſeene by the counſell, or brought about by the ſtrength of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the Magiſtrats of <hi>Grecia.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT will not greeue you, I know, neither will you thinke much, to giue ouer armes at laſt, and begone; who notwithſtanding, I haue ſo oft vanquiſht you in the field, yet, as I heare, you ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire your broken forces, and ſtill prepare for warre: It becomes conquerers to bid battell, and the conquered to obey their lawes; we hold it therefore ſafer for you to entertaine equal conditions of peace, then to be vanquiſhed againe in warre, and ſo to loſe both peace, and armes; for when the field is loſt, deliberation comes too late.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Magiſtrats of <hi>Grecia</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVE will not giue our backs with a fare-well to armes, before we encounter thee &amp; beat backe againe thoſe iniuries by which thou ſo often glorieſt in a fooliſh madneſſe, thou haſt triumphed ouer vs in the field; for, thou canſt not be ignorant, how doubtfully hangs the euent of things, and how changeablely the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fortune of warre reeles from the one to the other ſide. We ſcorne that peace, thou offereſt vs with ſlauery, and wouldeſt haue vs accept as conquered men; as for thy good counſell, keepe it to thy ſelfe; enemies are not to be conſulted with for the good of actions twixt vs and them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Venetians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu trouble, I heare, and moleſt the ſea coaſts of Licia with your Nauy, you prouided ſo great a one for the vſe of war by ſea; and not onely ſo, but after you had waſted with fire
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13074:11"/>
and ſword the borders of my Kingdome all ouer, you haue beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, I heare, Athalia, a Citie of Pamphilia: Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>er, I pray you, what concluſion will follow vpon theſe premiſes; he is foole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hardy and vnaduiſed that by warre aſſaults another mans eſtate, when he can hardly defend his owne; for it behoues and ſtands you vpon, ſince you loſt Colchis, to preſerue rather the common wealth, and vphold ſtill the old dignity of your name, then by vnlikely armes to ſeeke after anew Empire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Venetians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>NEither Peloponneſus, nor Colchis, themſelues, tho loſt long ſince by the deſtiny and ſentence of warre, can dant or diſcourage our minds from new aſſaults; howſoeuer thou broughteſt thoſe cuntries vnder thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, not by manhood of ſouldiers, but wonne to thy hand by a treacherous betraying of our men; we notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, who ſeeke not to gaine kingdomes by treachery, but victory by armes, haue laboured by our Nauy to make all things by all meanes offenſiue to thee and thine by ſea and land; for he is farre from the vertuous minde of a generous Prince, that inlargeth his dominion with Cities not taken by the Law of armes, but ſtollen by the falſe play of hidden guile.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Genuenſians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Heare that Menedorus in his Orations before the people, doth often brand my name with the blackneſſe of foule diſgrace, as if by his ill ſpeaking, he could worke vs any iniury, who haue learned long ſince to feare no words: but you are greatly deceiued; for we warre with you not by bitter gall of words, but by deeds of armes and dint of ſwords; he can eaſily contemne what men ſay of him, and laugh to heare his enemies raile on him, who for the loue of Lordſhips, and deſire of more Kingdomes, would not ſhun in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy it ſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:13074:12"/>
               <head>The <hi>Genuenſians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>NEither doth Menedorus by the authority of our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours, neither doe our Citizens by the decrees of our Citie purſue thee with diſgrace, but by a certaine inbred and vnappeaſeable hate of thee, who haſt made all men thine enimies, and prouoked them vnto iniury: as for the iniuries we haue receiued at thy hands, be thou well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, we goe not about to requite them with words, but meane to repay them with our ſwords: it skils but a little in our opinion, what men ſay of thee; thy deeds will not let fame belie thee; and thy ſhameleſſe diſhoneſty of an ill led life is now become ſenſeleſſe againſt all regard of honeſty.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Naritians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE accuſe, ô Naritians, your fooliſh madneſſe, not in a feare of warre, but in that you perſwade your ſelues, I purpoſely and of mine owne accord beare armes againſt you, as if ſillie worthleſſe mice were a worthy pray for the kingly Lion: is it not aſhame, if the Elephant ſhould ſtriue with Gnats?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Naritians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVE would to God thou didſt ſo ſcorne the Nariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, as an obiect of too low degree, and as a pray too baſe for thy braue minde; then ſhould our eies be leſſe fixed on thy power, and hearts leſſe troubled with thy might. But pardon vs that haue ſuffered ſo many e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils of our enemies, if experience and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of by-paſt times make vs looke about, and haue a care of time to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13074:12"/>
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Corcyrians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu haue confeſſed an iniurie, ô Corcyrians, whiles you make hauocke in the borders of Ambrachia, and ſpoile euery where the fields of Acarnania, turning all things to your owne pray, notwithſtanding I haue ſo oft formerly forgiuen you. But let thoſe men that are ſo forward, as to be firſt in iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries towards others, expest a day of paiment with vſurie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Corcyrians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>THou art much and more, miſtaken, if thou ſuppoſeſt, we onely confeſſed an iniury, and did no more. For we haue beſides brought deſolation vpon thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and left behind vs euery where the ſenſible teſtimonies of warre; therefore did we firſt raiſe warre againſt thee, to inuite our vertues vnto greater exploits, and to rowſe vp our reſolutions for greater indeuours; For we cannot with pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience indure the inhumaine cruelty of a Tyrant, that by all kinde of inhumanity and lawleſſe luſt hath offered violence to all ſorts of men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the king of <hi>Cyprus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AT the Calends of Auguſt I came with an Army into Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licia to winne the moſt opulent citie Tharſia; as for Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, the Legat of thy nauie, we ſlew him taken priſoner not farre from Phreata. See thou therefore vnto whoſe hands thy fathers kingdome now is come, feare Fortunes inconſtancie, for in humane things nothing is in all reſpects, and alwaies happy, or conſtant in happineſſe without change.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The King of <hi>Cyprus</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVHen by force of Armes I demanded Cyprus, mine owne, againe, I put to flight mine enemies at the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13074:13"/>
mountaines Ceraunia, not by any power I borowed of my fathers kingdome, whoſe fortune was then to liue at Carree a baniſhed man, deſtitute and far diſtant from mine owne; yet notwithſtanding by and by, ſo ſoone as I once entred the Iland with but a little band of men, I vanquiſhed with a handfull, incredible heapes of our enimies, in ſo much that all men ſaid, I had outgone Euagoras. Its not then by chance and peraduentures, but by wiſdome and ſouldiers valour, that wee manage our affaires, neither doe we glory ſo much in what we haue well done, as we fore-thinke and prouide for things to come. As for Fortune, ſhe is more to be feared of thee, whom ſhe ſeemes to haue lifted vp ſo high that ſhe may giue thee a greaterfall, and whom ſhe ſeemes now to fawne ſo much vpon in the fortunate ſucceſſe of things, that ſhe may more eaſily deceiue thee brought a bed in a fooles paradiſe with too much felicity to commit all things to Fortunes hazard; and to ſtay our ſelues, on her reſtleſſe wheele, I know not whether it be more vncertainty or more foole-hardineſſe in a man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Methonenſians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NEither will we, ô Methonenſians, as yet ſet vpon your City, neither yet will we that it free and ſecure from the aſſault of our Army, till by long protracted and continued warre, your Citizens turne warre into hatred, and hate armes, as their greateſt harmes. For ſo fares it with men, whoſe liues are in a continuall labour with a truceleſſe ſiege of ſickeneſſe, till in an irke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome tediouſneſſe of weary languiſhment, death becomes more deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then length of life; life now held their foe, and death their friend.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Methonenſians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>LIttle, or leſſe then nothing, haue we alwaies eſteemed thoſe armes, which ſtrike terrour to cowards, and bring with them faint-harted feare to white liuered men; but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13074:13"/>
adde no vertue to valorous minds. Thou maieſt doe well to ſpare thy ſelfe, and ſaue that care thou haſt of vs; for we haue learned to beare aduerſity, without the counſell of our enimies. We would thou ſhouldſt well know, thoſe armes can neuer be turned to hate, which woorthy Citizens haue tatken vp to defend their country, and countries liberty, with Parents, Wiues and Children, againſt the vnbridled luſt of lawleſſe Tyrants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Cretians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>IT hath alwaies beene lawfull, euen by the ordinances of our aunceſtors, to anſwer violence with violence, and to crie quit for quo with craft; neither yet doe wee tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the rules of friendſhip, when we onely reuenge the iniuries of our enemies: but with what face doſt thou call on vs, for fidelitie, branding vs with ſo blacke an imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as is falſhood vnder the colour of faith, ſeeing thou thy ſelfe haſt neuer kept truth with any?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the men of <hi>Chios.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE haue returned you againe, ô Chions, your tribute money; for when we conſidered the greatneſſe of your merits towards vs, we preſently decreed your freedome, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, Be you free; for its not money, but affection and fidelity thats required of friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The men of <hi>Chios</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>NOt what we deſire, when we remember thy ſo great liberality towards vs; (for then euen wiſhes come ſhort of our deſires, needes muſt then our abilitie come farre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, as neuer able to giue a bodie vnto our wiſhes, nor accompliſhment to our deſires) but what we are able, wee giue thee now and euer, immortall thanks; our comfort
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13074:14"/>
yet is this; well may our friends ſurpaſſe vs in facultie, and goe beyond vs in abilitie, but ouercome vs they ſhall not in liberalitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Epidaurians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Abideans, Phrygians, and Dardans, as I heare, who before were the onely Pyrats on all the ſeas, are now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trapt and ſurprized at Milas, as alſo put to death by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie ſorts of torments. You haue done well, I would thinke, by the lawes of armes; yet we cannot but account it abſurd, that you burned the gallies and gally-foists with fire; for warre is not with ſenſeleſſe ſhips (what ſhould they feele?) but with the men that manage them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Epidaurians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>NOt onely the death of captiued pyrats, but alſo the fireing of the ſhips is warranted by the rules of warre, the one for that they haue ſo oft troubled and indamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged vs by inuaſions; the other for that they lodged tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and brought theeues into our borders: we thought it therefore meet to burne the ſhips, together with the ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for oft had they runne away with the bootie of our goods, and tranſported our ſpoiles into Aſia. Now are not the weapons wherewith we are ſet vpon, to be numbred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our enemies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Nauplenſians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVIll you neuer giue ouer, nor make an end of iniuries, ô Nauplenſians? becauſe you haue ſet foote within the borders of Achaia, and by your often inuaſions, led away many a man for ſpoile; becauſe you thriue in ill doing, will you not ceaſe to doe ill? for how can it be, that men ſhut vp with ſiege, and cloſe priſoners to feare, ſhould put to ſword the townes of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13074:14"/>
conquerour, and waſte his fieldes with fire? doe not they ſeeme too late to prouide for the good of their countrey, who when all things are deſperate, venture vpon impoſſibilities, and caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues on all extremities?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Nauplenſians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>FOr our natiue countries ſake, the common mother of vs all, and for the ſafetie of our Citizens, as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good that ſits ſo neere vs all, to which two things we owe our ſelues and all thats ours, doe we willingly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice our liues, and obiect them to all extremities. For ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will we die with honour in the defence of our country, and maintenance of our freeborne liberty; or els (as victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie may fall on our ſide) our hands ſhall keepe our neckes from the heauie yoke of tyrannie, and preſerue vs ſtill for terme of life, our ancient freedome. For we eſteeme no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more glorious then to preferre our countries libertie before our parents, our children, and all things els.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Pannonians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HOwſoeuer, ô Pannonians, you haue oft giuen triall, how great your man-hood is in warre, yet haue you alwaies found it in experience, how little you haue got by it, if you compare your goods and ils together. For they that beare ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macks greater then their ſtrength, and cary minds larger then the meaſure of their owne power, haue euer beene too raſh in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, and impotent in vndergoing warre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Pannonians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVE come not to aske counſell of thee vnto our wars, we chalenge thee not for want of wiſdome to order thy affaires, neither will we require a reaſon of our enemie for thoſe armes he beares againſt vs,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13074:15"/>
for they haue wit enough to doe their buſineſſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage their actions, that by valour of minde and conſtancie, haue purchaſed themſelues victory with praiſe:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Macedonians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur Ambaſſadours brought me that you gaue them in charge: whereby you prouokt me rather vnto pitie than vnto hate; for it ſeemed to become you farre better, who haue beene conquered ſo oft, and brought ſo oft to be ſuters on your knees, to receiue with thanks, and not to offer with ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie the conditions of peace: is it not ſhame, that men in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie by war ſhould ſtand on proud termes with their conquerors?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Macedonians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>WHat iuſt and equal peace can there be twixt thee and the Macedonians? we deſire and endeuour to defend our country, and our lawes; thou not content with thine owne, thirſteſt after other kingdomes by force of armes, and ſeekeſt to ſtretch out thine Empire beyond thy bounds: we cannot but ſpeake touching our common-wealth, as it becomes our conſtancie and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous mindes, that we hold nothing dearer, and ſweeter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, then libertie; yet this hath alwaies beene the common vice and fault of tyrants; free ſtates they hate to death, free cities ſtand too much in their ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Aſiaticks.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur Ambaſſadors deliuered their ambaſſage at Zizicus. In words, it ſeemes, you are our friends, and confederates vnto armes; but in deed and trueth, you are our enemies. Either ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſend vs in all haſte large ſhips for aſſistance, or chuſe vnto you warre: for the affection of friends conſists not in words, but in deeds, when need requireth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:13074:15"/>
               <head>The <hi>Aſiaticks</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>THat we promiſe many things before thee by the mouth of our Ambaſſadors, and performe but fewe things, of what we promiſed, the one was the iſſue of thankfull mindes; the other muſt be aſcribed to wants. We ſent thee preſents by Mearchus, which if they ſeeme leſſe then thy deſert, and too little for thy greatneſſe; yet well maieſt thou thinke them greater then our abilitie is able wel to giue; howſoeuer thankfulneſſe makes vs ſtretch out our hands beyond our reach.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Bithynians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu neither ſent vs ſhips for the vſe and ſeruice of warre, nor yet money in due time. We accuſe therefore and charge you with vnfriendly backwardneſſe. Take heed, I pray you, how you make them angrie with you, and prouoke them to hoſtile indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whom you now ſeeme to contemne with neglect. For its bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alwaies to take vp voluntarie armes againſt our enemies, then after many dammages and manifold indignities to be enforced to the field.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Bithynians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>THe ſhips we loſt of late, conquered vnto aſhes by the furie of the fierie conquerour, come to the number of twiſe ten in all; as for the reſt of our ſhips, ſome ſplit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues on hardie rocks at Malea, and found to their owne vndooing, that ſtones are ſtronger; ſome periſhed in the conflict with our enemies; the ſea ſwallowed others vp, by drowning ſaued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other deaths; yet dead &amp; drowned are both but one; this periſheth as well as that. For our money, its run low; our treaſurie is neere drawn dry, by feeding the fire of warre ſo long: thou therefore for thy humanitie par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, we pray thee, thoſe whom Fortune hath made ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13074:16"/>
for how can they giue that haue their hands cut off? and what can they giue, that licke their knife?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Coronenſians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ARe you not aſhamed, ô Coronenſians, after you haue beene thrice ouerthrowen in open field, and ouercome on euen ground, to reuiue battell yet againe, and yet againe to patch vp an army? do you therfore ſo often reiterate armes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue old warres, that late repentance, may the oftner make rods for your follie, and bring a potion in her hand when all is too late and life is gone? If the bent and aime of thoſe armes you beare againſt vs, be for the purchaſe of peace, we pardon your feare; if in a hope of victory, conſidering your caſe ſo deſperate, your ſtate and ſtrength at ſo low an ebbe, we accuſe your madneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Coronenſians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVHatelſe doe they that often raiſe warre againſt their enemies, but ſhew themſelues more then moſt deſirous of peace? For no peace can be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, nor ſecurity eſtabliſhed to Citizens with hope of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, without warring with their aduerſaries, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to their oppoſites. The arbitrement of war and peace, conſiſts in victory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Florentines.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur Merchants, which trafficke in Pontus and Galatia, ſent to intreate vs at Theſſalonica for freedome from tribute, and toultakers, with free cariage and recariage. We therefore, that delight in nothing more, and hold nothing more honorable, then to exerciſe liberality towards our friends (liberality, the faireſt and louelieſt of vertues:) haue granted and freely giuen the liberties and priuiledges of our City to your Citizens; for, who beſtowes a benefit on weldeſeruing men, ſeemes not ſo much to giue any thing, as to requite a good turne.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13074:16"/>
               <head>The <hi>Florentines</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVE will eaſily yeeld to thee, as far inferiour to ſtriue with thee in greatneſſe of good-turnes: but pardon vs, if we will not be ouercome in thankefulneſſe of minde: the abundance of our harts ſhall make ſome amends for the ſhortneſſe of our hands: for we haue alwaies prized it high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and valued it in the height of affection, that thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt doe a thing ſo plauſible to our Citizens, and ſo woorthy of thy ſelfe; yet can we not, but account it a matter of more woorth in loues eſtimation, that we repay thee with more then our purſes are well able to beare; for the woorth of a benefit goes not by the greatneſſe of the thing it ſelfe; but it is the minde and good-will of the giuer, that ſets the price on what is giuen, which can be recompenced with nought but with the ſame againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Pontians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE haue ſent you home againe the Merchant-ſhips we tooke priſoners in the Aegean ſeas, which moleſted the Ocean as ſo many blockehouſes: but not to curry fauour, I call the Gods to witneſſe, nor yet to be rewarded, haue I done ſo with you; for we verily hold it greater glory to giue, then take; and out of our liberality to returne all men double for what we take.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Pontians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>TO be large hearted, and liberally handed towards all men, what elſe is it in very deed, but to deſerue the hearts and tongues of all men? ſo gracious a vertue is liberalitie, and of ſuch an attractiue power. Thy huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and vnmerited fauour in ſending vs home our ſhippes againe, hath made them that were once thy foemen, now for euer thy faſt friends and ſworne confederates to beare a part
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13074:17"/>
in all thy wars, ſo comely and louely is it to change iniuries into fauours, and make peace of warre.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Cretians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ITs very diſhonorable to vs and our State, ô Cretians, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and continue a league of friendſhip, with them, that in their deeds ſhew themſelues to practiſe war, rather then peace, and vnder the vizor of friends, to play the part of foes: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider I beſeech you, how ſafe and good it will be for you, to feare them anon as your enemies, whom before when they were your friends, you contemned without right or reaſon. Repentance is the follower of raſh attempts; and hath oft ouertaken many a bold beginner.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Great Turke to the <hi>Delphians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NEither the Oracles of your God Apollo, nor Aeſculapius your God of Phyſicke could cleere you altogether of frenſie, who ſo vnaduiſed haue ordered matters, that euen Minerua her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the Goddes of aduice, cannot giue aduice in ſo great folly and madneſſe. For the inrfirmities of the body be oftentimes healed, good meanes being vſed; but no remedy or medicine is of force to cure the diſeaſe of the minde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Delphians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>IT ſeemes indeed that we haue taken ſmall aduice and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed but little diſcretion in managing our affairs; yet it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out with vs as it doth for the moſt part with Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who haue skil in other mens ſickneſſes to find the cauſe and worke the cure, but ſeldome or neuer helpe and heale themſelues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to them of Pergamum.</head>
               <p>KNow you, the Gouernours and inhabitants of Pergamum, that we haue vndertaken a voiage, intending to bend our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13074:17"/>
forces againſt the Euboeians. Wherefore it is our will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that you meete vs at Marathon, that by this meanes you, who haue alwaies manifeſted your faithfullneſſe towards vs as occaſion was offered, may now alſo ſhew your readineſſe &amp; ſpeed when neede requireth. They deſerue double thanks who not onely beſtow kindneſſe very frankely, but giue that which they beſtow, if not without asking, yet without delay.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Pergamenians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVE are ready to ſet forwards to the warres with a great fleet, not onely to multiply and encreaſe your forces, but alſo to giue a more fierce aſſault and lay ſorer ſiege againſt the Chalcidenſians. They deſerue but ſmall thanks who cheerefully performe their bounden duty, when they haue ability and opportunity to do it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Mitylenians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough the faithfulneſſe of you of Mitylene hath bene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore ſo apparant that we neuer made doubt of the ſame, notwithſtanding you neuer manifeſted the ſame more then in this (which I heare of late) that you haue not ſuffered your enemies and ours to take poſſeſſion of your citie, but ſhut the gates againſt them: For you are farre from that perfediouſneſſe which is in ſome, who are ready vpon euery profer to entertaine new friends and new factions. You hold it a matter ſo glorious to defend with force of armes your country and ſtate, when you may doe it without violation of the Lawes of friendſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>They of <hi>Mitylene</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>THe Mitylenians, who hauing now no face of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth left muſt liue in perpetuall ſubiection and ſlauery, haue thought it farre better to remaine vnder the gouernment of one, then to make triall of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13074:18"/>
of many; wherefore you ought not ſo much to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue our fidelity in this, as admire our prouidence and policy. For we doe not propound them to our ſelues as paterns and examples for imitation, who being ſicke of an incurable diſeaſe take aduice of a multitude of Phyſitians; and notwithſtanding they vſe many and diuerſe medicines, yet are neuer reſtored to health of body.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Amazonians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF that for the maintenance of the franchiſment and liberty of Citizens you Amazonians did wage warre againſt me, I ſhould not ſo much hold you my enemies as good citizens who tooke armes in defence of their Country, Children, and Parents: but there is no reaſon of force to perſwade vs that they will now refuſe to ſubiect themſelues to men, who heeretofore ſo long time indured the dominion and principality of women.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Amazonians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>THe raigne and gouernment of the Amazons, which you ſeeme to caſt in our teeth as a reproch &amp; diſgrace, doth incourage and prouoke vs not to giue obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to any other; for nothing can be more diſgracefull for men, then to be found effeminate, yea more faint-harted than women; wherefore thinke ſuch men to be in warre in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible and moſt worthy of Soueraignty, amongſt whom euen ſilly women haue learned to ſway an Empire.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Sclauonians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu are neither able to defend your citie by force of armes, nor any longer to endure the ſiege wherewith you are begirt; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you muſt needs either take lawes as men conquered, or els remooue the ſiege, by putting to flight the forces of him that ſeeks to bring you into thraldome. Certainly they haue but little wit,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13074:18"/>
who being depriued of all aide and ſuccour from their confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, prolong the warre to the great loſſe and hinderance of a common-wealth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Sclauonians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVHereas you are not ignorant that we alwaies haue had a deſire and reſolution to maintaine and holde our freedome, we haue not yet giuen ouer the hope where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we anchored; neither indeed is it poſſible that Fortune ſhould make our ſtate more miſerable, whoſe caſe is ſo bad, that it is euen deſperate and paſt cure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Rhodians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF you Rhodians had but as much might as will, and as much ſtrength as valour, I ſhould thinke you were not to be conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by any whatſoeuer: but ſeeing the neceſſaries and nerues of warre be men, horſe, munition, money and victuals, you ought rather to haue regard to your owne eſtate, then vnaduiſedly to prouoke vs to come in battell againſt you; for it is not all one to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed your enemies in courage of minde, and to be able to ouercome them by might and force of armes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Rhodians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>IT is not vnknowne vnto you that we haue alwaies had as well might &amp; ſtrength, as courage and will, and that you haue ſufficiently proued by the many, and them no ſmall, ouerthrowes your men haue receiued by vs: we haue made plentifull prouiſion and preparation of all things that can be expedient, or neceſſary for vs in theſe affaires, ſo that the policie, prouidence, and wiſedome of the Rhodians at home, will driue you to no leſſe admiration of them, then their proweſſe and manhood abroad: And we are thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, though our forces be not ſo great as yours, that you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13074:19"/>
ſhall vanquiſh vs rather for want of good Fortune then good courage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Rhodians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Vnderſtand that you of Rhodes haue alreadie enuironed your citie with deepe trenches, and fortified the wals with three great rampiers, and haue linked vp the harborough towards Mandrachium Coloſſi with iron chaines, that your Citie may be free from incurſion and inrodes of enemies, and we diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and with held from laying ſiege vnto you. A matter indeed woorthy to be remembred and ſpoken of. For what is more glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious for a man then to venture his life in fighting for his liberty, countrey, children, and parents, that the common-wealth may be preſerued? But I pray you by that immortall God whom you ſerue, what courage haue you to reſiſt our forces by ſea and land, with ſo great preparation? For ſeeing we haue after aſſault ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and vanquiſhed that famous citie Conſtantinople, the Ile Metelin, the countries of Morea and Colchis, it were better and more befitting you, to beware by others calamitie, &amp; follow their example in yeelding, then to make your ſelues a ſpectacle to others of miſerie and deſtruction. They who audaciouſly attempt matters beyond their ſtrength, for the moſt part ſuffer condigne puniſhment of ſuch foole-hardineſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Rhodians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>YOu ought not ſo much to make relation to vs of the captiuitie of the Grecians, as to ſet vs before others as a paterne of fortitude and valour: who as we haue a more iuſt cauſe to take vp armes, ſo we haue greater confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of better ſucceſſe. You had the ouerthrow by vs once at the Iland Coes or Langa, and twiſe at the citie Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lymnum; we alſo beſetting the armies of the Soldan king of Babylon, ouerthrew him, and put him to flight. Yea moreouer, the Admirals of Rhodes haue often made warre
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13074:19"/>
againſt the Egyptians, Syrians, and Phoenicians. Doe not therefore blame and reproch vs for confidence, who haue preuailed and got the better againſt ſo many nations, who may ſooner make others more reſolute againſt you by our example, then any whit be diſcouraged by the rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of them you haue made your vaſſals.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Epirotes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE vnderſtood by the Ambaſſadors of Moloſſia of late that Dyrrachium, Apolonia, and all that part of Scla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonia, is annoied and moleſted by the incurſions and forraging of our armies; and they told vs that theeues lie in waite by the way ſide, in euery narrow paſſage, &amp; that nothing in Macedonia is in ſafetie. You inhabitants of Epire, we haue long ſince giuen ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient credite to all they haue informed vs of: but our maner is to trie our right by dint of ſword: wherefore I ſuppoſe it a matter more beſeeming you, (if you call to minde your former valour) to take reuenge on them that doe you wrong, then by your Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours vainely to make complaint to vs of them; for the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of a mans enemie is hindered not by oratorie, but by force of armes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Epirotes</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>INdeed if it were free for vs, and we had power to doe it by deeds of armes, we had rather our ſelues be reuenged on our enemies that offer vs iniuries, then intreat of theſe things before you by our Ambaſſador: but ſeeing we are too weake to compaſſe it, we haue thought it more for our ſafety to ſue to our enemies for peace, then vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take warre to no purpoſe or profite. For it ought to be thought no leſſe valour, then policie to foreſee and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all things by good aduice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13074:20"/>
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Dalmatians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE enioyned you the paiment a certaine taxe and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie, which ſeeing you brought in later then was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, you make vs to thinke that you doe it grudgingly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly; wherefore either approoue your faithfulneſſe towards vs in deeds, which need requires, otherwiſe we will proceed againſt you in hoſtilitie, and manifeſt to the world that we eſteeme you as enemies. Diſſembling and double dealing is as vnmeet amongst friends as may be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Dalmatians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>YOu ſhould rather blame our want of abilitie in this caſe, then our backwardneſſe, for it is not poſſible, that he ſhould pay ſubſidies, that hath no meanes to get money, where nothing is to be had, the king muſt loſe his right; wherefore they are not to be eſteemed as enemies, who are ſtill faithfull to their friends, though they cannot expreſſe it by their bountifull gifts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Apulians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE are purpoſed once againe to returne vnto the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Brutians, and all Apulia, farre and neere, to make iuſt warre againſt them, who as we haue forcibly brought into ſubiection the Grecians, and ioined them to our Empire, now alſo make preparation to inuade with our forces that coaſt of Italie, which heeretofore was called great Graecia. You therefore wiſely imitating the ancient inhabitants of thoſe parts, make ſurrender of your ſelues, and your cities into our hands: it ſeemes to be a great ſhame for good Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens to reuolt from the cuſtomes of their Anceſtors, and Lawes of their countrie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:13074:20"/>
               <head>The <hi>Apulians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>THey which make their owne will a law, doe declare that all the right and title they haue, is by their force in armes. But you (although you will vs to follow the lamentable example of the Grecians) doe not ſo much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to perſwade vs to the imbracing of their lawes, as to the entertaining of that gouernment which they are brought vnder: but it is impoſſible that we ſhould become more rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to yeeld our ſelues to your mercy then others, ſeeing you haue moſt cruelly put to death ſuch men of ours, as you haue taken captiue, omitting no torments that you could inflict vpon them: For kingdoms are eaſily gotten, and inlarged by mercy, liberality, and iuſtice; but can hardly be kept with any force whatſoeuer if they be tyrannically dealtwithall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Brunduſians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVE haue intelligence by the Embaſſadours of Calabria of your gallant hauens and ports to harbour our ſhips in, and of the ſituation of your Citie. Therefore we appoint you together with the men of Otronto to aſſociate vs to the warres, for we are preparing to conuey ouer our forces into Italy, intending with an huge Army to accompliſh our victories. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it doth not beſeeme you, nor is it good for you to contemne, or ſet light by him, whom his owne ſubiects may loue for his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and his enemies feare for his ſtrength and force in armes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Brunduſians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>ARe you not aſhamed to inuite them as confederates to take part with you in a moſt wicked and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble warre, who haue alwaies ſhewed themſelues of all men moſt bitter enemies againſt you? It is moſt deteſtable
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13074:21"/>
to ſerue in the warres vnder ſuch a Tyrant, who after victory will haue the captiuated ſubiect themſelues vnto him, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his cruelty, villany and abhominable luſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to them of <hi>Saragoſa.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOu Syracuſians, I vnderſtand, that you, they of Agrigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, the Meſſanians, and Cathanians haue combined your ſelues together and conſpired againſt vs, for the reſtoring to the Grecians their former liberties and franchiſes: we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are prouiding an huge Army to conduct to Syracuſa from Morea in Greece, that now at laſt you may feele the hoſtility of them, whom before you without all equity ſcorned to be your confederates.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Syracuſians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>IF we haue preſumed in confidence of our ability, and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy in waging warre to take vp armes againſt you, we are not to be thought to haue attempted any thing raſhly and vnaduiſedly againſt our enemy. For with how much the more equity, and right men fight for their country and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, they are made ſo much the more reſolute and in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hope of victory.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the Gouernours of <hi>Italie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Vnderſtand that Germany, France, and Spaine are in armes againſt vs, and that you haue exhibited to them Captaines and Generals for the managing of the warre. They ſeeme to haue little care, and regard of their owne good and ſecurity, who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly without any cauſe at all prouoke their enemies to war.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Gouernours of <hi>Italie</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>THe cauſe of our warre cannot but be moſt iuſt, who in deteſtation of the cruelty and villany of a moſt vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13074:21"/>
Tyrant doe take armes againſt you, as againſt a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like enemy of nature. We haue not onely conſpired with the Germans, French men, Spaniards, and all the Eaſt countries, but haue ſollicited the free-townes euery where to rebell againſt the Turkiſh Nation: and therefore the moſt rich and puiſſant Kings of the Chriſtians by our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion haue muſtered vp their forces, and are riſen in armes to be reuenged on you for your cruelties, fury, maſſacres, murders, abhominable luſt, burning and ſacking of Cities, and to ſet free the whole world from ſuch outragious iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. That warre is moſt iuſtly vndertaken which being neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, the common ſafety of all is indangered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to King <hi>Ferdinand.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Am very glad to heare of your worthy praiſes, inuincible cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and managing of your affaires to your great glorie and eſtimation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who, when you haue ſo often ouerthrowen your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, haue onely reſpected this in your victories, that you might be gracious in pardoning them whom you conquered: and not ſo much that your enemies might feele your iuſt reuenge, hauing prouoked you thereunto, as that euery one might know, and haue experience of your mercifulneſſe and clemencie. And that which we account a matter of greateſt commendation in a Prince, you haue alwaies ſhewed your ſelfe inuincible, and not cast downe in aduerſitie, when Fortune hath croſſed you; and in proſperity, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proud nor puffed vp. Wee haue willingly made relation of theſe good parts, and the rather becauſe vertue as it is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable in a mans aduerſary, ſo it wanteth not due commendations oftentimes from the mouth of an enemie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>ALthough we hold it a glory and credit to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended of our enemies for our great deſerts, becauſe their teſtimonie and approbation is for the moſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13074:22"/>
part true, and friends in ſhew prooue flatterers in deed, and ſo deceiue vs in their teſtimonie of vs: Notwithſtanding we doe not ſo much ſtand vpon, or delight in any mans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations in words, as we deſire that our owne woorthy and notable deeds ſhould make vs famous. Howbeit I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly imbrace this your teſtimonie of me, that you thinke me to be ſuch a one, whom for vertue and good parts euer his enemies may admire, and for iuſt dealing, his ſubiects and Citizens may honour, and reuerence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Sicilians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Carthaginian captaines, who in times paſt, ſo long while contended with the Romans for principalitie, haue giuen you many ouerthrowes, and brought you to great ruine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſeldome kept league with them, but tooke part with their enemies. And now I vnderſtand that you haue ſent aide to the Rhodians at Halicarnaſſus, and haue conueied thither in your ſhips of carriage all furniture and prouiſion for warre. Wherefore we denounce you to be our enemies, and will declare the ſame by al hoſtility, that they which were ſo vnaduiſed, as to ſo little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to offend vs, without any cauſe to wrong vs, may ſuffer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne puniſhment of ſuch audacious raſhneſſe. For it will be not onely for our ſafetie to reuenge the iniuries that other men doo vnto vs, but it will make our enemies to feare vs the more.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Sicilians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>NEither haue we taken vp armes againſt you, howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer you accuſe vs that we ſent aide to the Rhodians in Halicarnaſſus, nor may we be thought to do anie man wrong if we chooſe rather to aide our faithfull confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, then a moſt cruell tyrant. You may but badly caſt in our teeth, the perfidiouſneſſe and vnfaithfulneſſe of our aunceſtors, who your ſelfe neuer kept truce or oath with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and you are vnwiſe to goe about with bugge-bearers
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13074:22"/>
and threatning wordes to feare and terrifie them, who are more ready to referre the ſuppoſed iniuries to the triall of fire and ſword, then determination of words.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Alexandrians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Haue interdicted, yee men of Alexandria, all Pontus and Aſia to your marchants. For the cities of Bithinia being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted in great ſummes of money, ſent their Ambaſſadours from Callipolis to complaine vnto mee, holding alſo in great dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation the vſurie of the merchants, wherewith all cities are emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied of their money. We hold it therefore better, to prouide for the good of many, then for the profit of a few.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Alaxandrians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>THough it belongeth not to vs to contend with thee about priuate matters, yet if theſe things whereof thou writeſt, haue beene done or attempted by any, thou canſt deſerue for this at our hands neither loue nor hate, ſeeing euery man is permitted to doe as he liſt in his owne affaires.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Tartarians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHereas others are many times made wicked either by ſome feare, or through neceſſitie, you by the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the place where yee liue, are of all men liuing the woorſt and vildeſt, being a rude and barbarous multitude without gouernment and without lawe. But foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as you haue ſent neither money nor Ambaſſadours in time vnto vs, you ſhew euidently that we muſt get both with force.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:13074:23"/>
               <head>The <hi>Tartarians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>TRuly thou art woorſe then madde to exact any thing of vs, who doe liue our ſelues vpon the ſpoiles of others: and in vaine doſt thou expect an Ambaſſage from thoſe who neuer learned to intreat, but to fight. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther oughteſt thou to woonder at our maners, ſeeing they are ſo little differing from thoſe of beaſts. For they which haue beene taught by their anceſtors to haue no lawe but armes, vſe maſſacres for a pray, and ſpoiles for law.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Athenians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOur Schooles, ô Athenians, whereby you haue attained to a moſt flouriſhing Eſtate, and to the chiefeſt name and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of all good learning and Philoſophie, doe perſwade mee much to ſpare your citie, aſwell for the reuerence which I beare to the wiſedome and honour of our anceſtors, as alſo through the loue which I haue euer carried to the ſtudie of thoſe good Arts, which I haue heard were firſt inuented, and afterward made perfect in Athens. But on the other ſide, when I conſider your malice alwaies againſt me, I cannot but thinke, my kindneſſe doth rather prouoke you to hate me, then mooue you any way to be thankfull. Therefore hauing waſted the whole territorie of Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſina, from Pyerus to Megara, I haue giuen the ſame to be the pray and ſpoile of my ſouldiours, and am readie in like maner to ſacke the citie: For the inſolencie of an offendour many times exceedeth and deſtroieth the mercy of an enemie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Athenians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>VVE beare no hatred to thee, for our libertie ſaued; what cauſe haue we? But we haue taken armes for our countrey, for our children, for our parents, to whom we owe all we haue. Neither can we be ſaid to deale with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13074:23"/>
thee like enemies, when we defend our owne, conſidering thou thy ſelfe doeſt fight to take from others. But it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thee to haue regard what thing doth beſt comport with thy greatneſſe. Haue we offended thee? Sylla forgaue the Athenians: and twiſe was Alexander pleaſed to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don them. Truely, thy victorie cannot bee great, if thou wilt deſtroy vs that are the glory of thy conqueſt. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou oughteſt to ſaue vs for an example of thy clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that ſo thou maieſt allure all men to loue thee, rather then by exerciſing thy crueltie, luſt, and furie, vpon poore captiues, to prouoke all the Greekes to abhorre thee. As for vs, who haue no other hope or confidence left vs, if thou wilt not pardon vs, wee are reſolued valiantly to trie the woorſt of Fortune. For what is more honorable, or more pleaſing in the world to men of ſpirit and reſolution, then to die couragiouſly for the preſeruation and ſafetie of the common-wealth and countrey?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Thebanes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YEe men of Thebes, I heare you are angrie that I haue ſpoiled Athens, whom I haue obſerued long ſince to haue beene companions in armes, and of counſell against mee. To you therefore, who are alreadie poſſeſſed with an horrible feare of the enemie, the ſame end, the ſame deſtinie, and the ſame miſeries, that the Athenians felt, are reſerued, which I thought good to ſignifie vnto you, that you may be tormented, first with feare, and conſcience of your miſdeeds, and then with more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous puniſhments, and tortures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Thebanes</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>THe ruine of the Athenians hath doubled the ſtrength and courage, not onely of the Thebanes, but alſo of all the Greekes, whom we haue many times reſtored to their libertie; ſo as now growing madde with furie, they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13074:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
doe earneſtly purſue thee, to chaſtice all thy villanies. For in deepe afflictions, deſperate reſolutions are euer wont to promiſe an aſſured ſafetie. Neither can they that haue vſed to command others, be eaſely perſwaded to obey a tyrant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The Turke to the <hi>Lacedemonians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Heare, yee men of Sparta, that you are afraid of the armie which vnder the conduct of Cleander, I ſent to beſiege your citie, wherein are twentie thouſand choſen footmen, and eight thouſand of light horſemen: whoſe noble courage in war &amp; firme faith to me, not onely my ſelfe haue often tried, but the enemy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hath feared. Therefore it becommeth you being toſſed with ſo many miſeries of Fortune, to looke well to the preſeruation of the common-wealth, and ſafetie of your people: leſt if following the vertue of your aunceſtors, you vndertake a warre against me, which you are not able to mainteine; you be compelled to pay deerely for your raſhneſſe. For it is an excellent thing with yeeld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to deſerue well of an enemie. Which who ſo refuſeth now to doe willingly, ſhall be conſtrained ere long againſt his will.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>The <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> to the Turke.</head>
               <p>CLeander being with his armie againſt our citie of Sparta, of our owne accord we ſurrender our ſelues vnto him: for the Lacedemonians hold it ſafer to yeeld to the counſell of the enemie, when it is profitable, then to hazard the fortune of a battell. Neither doe wee eſteeme victorie to be ſo glorious vnto vs, as it is to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our countrie from the rage and furie of warre, without hurt or detriment to the eſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13074:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
